<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>client on WebVoxel Game Engine</title>
    <link>https://dans-stuff.github.io/blog/tags/client/</link>
    <description>Recent content in client on WebVoxel Game Engine</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 21:40:12 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://dans-stuff.github.io/blog/tags/client/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic Rendering of Voxels</title>
      <link>https://dans-stuff.github.io/blog/posts/basic_rendering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 21:40:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dans-stuff.github.io/blog/posts/basic_rendering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rendering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Test Code&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://dans-stuff.github.io/blog/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 20:51:23 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dans-stuff.github.io/blog/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dude&#34;&gt;The Dude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m Dan and I love difficult projects. My language of choice is Go, though I use native JavaScript when writing for the browser. If you want to contact me, my discord is SR|Dan#6804 and you can find me in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://discordapp.com/invite/anZVvmd&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-idea&#34;&gt;The Idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a few ideas I have had in the past for browser-based games, ranging from barebones survival games, to casual online first-person shooters, to a lobby based dungeon crawler, but the investment is just so high. Then I realized that voxels are actually a brilliant building block, as ironic as that may sound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most games and genres could play out perfectly well in a modified voxel engine. If there was a base voxel engine that just worked, then other games could be built on top of it. Creating an overhead RPG is just a matter of fixing the camera to 3rd person and rewiring the controls, creating an FPS is just fixing to a first person camera and hitscanning some projectiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-project&#34;&gt;The Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan is to create a voxel-centric engine that can be rapidly developed into web-based games. This means networking, such that a server can provide a voxel world and syncronize entities in that world. This means generation and world editing, such that the engine can work as it&amp;rsquo;s own level editor. This means efficient rendering of a multitude of voxel types, useful default systems such as light, voxel physics, particles, dynamic voxels, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is to document the project and the journey to creating it. It will contain technical breakdowns, engine work, design philosophy rambling, screenshots and demos, and hopefully some game development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img  src=&#34;banner.png&#34;
        alt=&#34;Voxel Landscape&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>